Guide to the Muriel Rukeyser Papers, 1927-1967
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Muriel Rukeyser Papers
1927-1967
Rukeyser, Muriel, 1913-1980
0.5 cubic feet (3 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
The Muriel Rukeyser Papers contain various published works and corresponding promotional materials in addition to manuscripts, including signed Neruda translations. Correspondence with the poet and photographs of The Colors of the Day complete the collection.
Biographical Note
Born 15 Dec 1913 in New York City, Muriel Rukeyser (VC Ex 1934) was an American poet and political activist. With a style ranging from lyrical to documentary, deeply affected by the social and political, Rukeyser worked in poetry, prose and drama. She died 12 February 1980 in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The Muriel Rukeyser Papers contain various published works and corresponding promotional materials in addition to manuscripts, including signed Neruda translations. Correspondence with the poet and photographs of The Colors of the Day complete the collection.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Neruda, Pablo, 1904-1973--Translations into English
Subjects:
Women poets; Poetry
VCL Categories
Literature and Writing; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Finding aid encoded by Jason Kovari, 24 Feb 2009.
Acquisition Information
Issues of Walden Splash donated by Jeanette Lambert, Laguna Hills, CA, 1988.
Four issues of Walden Splash donated by Barbara Newman Morris, London, U.K., 5 Apr 2005.
One letter donated by Congregation Emanu-El, New York, N.Y., 27 Sept 2008.
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1930-1965
- Series II. Publications, 1927-1967
- Series III. Manuscripts, 1953-1961
- Series IV. Photographs, 1961
- Series V. Publicity Materials, 1960-1961
Container List
- SERIES I. Correspondence
  - Rukeyser to Jeanette Lambert, 13 Oct 1930 (Folder 1.1)
  - Rukeyser to Fanny Borden, 2 Mar 1942 (Folder 1.2)
  - Rukeyser to Dorothy Plum, 1962-1963 (Folder 1.3)
  - Rosalie Tucker to Rukeyser, 1963 (Folder 1.4)
  - Dorothy Plum to Rukeyser, 1962-1964 (Folder 1.5)
  - Wislocki to Rukeyser, 1965 (Folder 1.6)
  - Rukeyser to Grace Proffitt, undated (Folder 1.7)
  - Fragments, (photocopy) (Folder 1.8)
- SERIES II. Publications
  - Libretto: The Colors of the Day, 1961 (Folder 1.9)
  - Playbill: The Colors of the Day, 1961 (Folder 1.10)
  - Postcard: "The Poem as Mask: Orpheus,", 1967 (Folder 1.11)
  - Walden Splash (vol. 12, no. 1), 1928 (Folder 1.12)
  - Walden Splash (vol. 14, no. 1), 1930 (Folder 1.13)
  - Walden Splash (vol. 19), 1935 (Folder 1.14)
  - Walden Splash, 1927-1930 (Folder 1.15)
  - Poem: XIX, 1953 (Folder 1.16)
- SERIES III. Manuscripts
  - "The Day of the Closing"/ "All the Way Home,", 1953 (Folder 1.17)
  - Notebook: The Colors of the Day, undated (Folder 1.18)
  - Script: The Colors of the Day (Author’s Presentation Copy), 1961 (Folder 2.1)
  - Translation of Pablo Neruda's "Pueblo Cautivo,", undated; (MS, signed) (Box 3)
  - Translation of Pablo Neruda's "Pueblo Cautivo,", undated; (TS, signed) (Box 3)
  - Translation of "Prisoner Land," author unknown, undated; (TS, signed) (Box 3)
- SERIES IV. Photographs
  - The Colors of the Day, 1961 (Folder 2.2)
- SERIES V. Publicity Materials
  - Book Jackets, Promotional Material (Folder 2.3)
  - Clippings, Press Release (Folder 2.4)
  - Press Release for V.C. Centennial, 1960 (Folder 2.5)
  - Program: The Alumnae Festival, 1961 (Folder 2.6)